Guide to the American Society of Civil Engineers, Stanford University Student Chapter, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
American Society of Civil Engineers, Stanford University student chapter, records
1896-1941
SC0525
American Society of Civil Engineers. Stanford University student chapter
3.75 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Associated Students of Stanford University.
Information about Access
None.
HISTORICAL NOTE
Civil engineering students at Stanford University organized their first professional club in 1893, the Civil Enginering Club. In November 1905, the Civil Engineering Society was organized; the name was changed to the Associated Civil Engineers in 1910. In 1920, when the American Society of Civil Engineers authorized student chapters, the Stanford A.C.E. became the first student chapter to join the A.S.C.E.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
These records represent both the Associated Civil Engineers and the Stanford University student chapter of the American Society of Civil Engineers. Records of the A.C.E. include an account book, 1905-1920, papers read before meetings, 1911-1915, and secretary's book, 1905-1919. Records of the student chapter of the American Society of Civil Engineers include constitution and related correspondence, correspondence of Samuel B. Morris pertaining to several research trips, abstracts of proceedings from national meetings, and several papers read before local meetings.
The bulk of these records were found among the records of the Associated Students of Stanford University. They were removed in December 1996 and processed as a separate collection. The record book of the Associated Civil Engineers was removed from the 4 digit collection and added to this collection.
Access Terms
Associated Civil Engineers. (Location of Meeting--Stanford University); Civil Engineering Society. (Location of Meeting--Stanford University.); Morris, Samuel Brooks, 1890-1962.; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Students.;; Thomas, William Henry.; Civil engineering.; Photoprints.
Collection Contents
- Associated Civil Engineers, record book, 1905-1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Papers read before the A.C.E.
  - Ambrose, A. W., Maintenance of Way Construction on the Southern Pacific (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Avery, H. T., California State Highway Construction, October 1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blase, Roy, Electrification of the Oakland Suburban System, May 1913 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Briggs, R. C., The Work of the U. S. Coast and Geodetic Survey (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brinkmeyer, H., Revaluation Work on Rail Roads, Jan. 26, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cecil, N. M., The Modesto and Turlock Irrigation Districts (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Christensen, A. E., Roads of the Middle West, Nov. 23, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cox, Joel B.
    - An Irrigation Ditch in Hawaii, May 1913 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - The New Haiku Ditch, April 1915 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dickinson, P. V., The Flood Problem of the Calaveras River Basin (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dingle, C. O., California State Roads, September 1911 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dodge, J. W., Automatic Telegraphy, November 1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dool, D. C., Controlling the Colorado River at the Imperial Valley Canal Intake, April 1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Doxsee, W. H., Proposed Development of Redwood Harbor, May 1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - George, H. P., The San Diego and Arizona Railway (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gill, G. F., Southern Pacific Surveying Methods, [missing pages 1 and 2], October 1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gregory, A. C., Levees and Levee Construction (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Halcombe, N. M., Canal Excavation in Shasta County (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hirasawa, J., Japanese Oil Production, December 1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hunt, G. W., A Modern Method of Locating Logging Roads, May 1913 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jack, J. R., Efficiency in a Manager (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jeffers, J. S., Failure of Wooden Girder Long Beach Wharf, March 1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Kingsbury, J. M., Experiences in the Oil Fields, December 1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Laird, W. A., Summerland Water Supply System (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - McMillan, W. Bruce, The Effect of Motor Traffic on Rock Roads (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Morrison, M. E., The Pittsburg Filtration Plant (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Narver, D. L., Tufa Cement as Used on the Los Angeles Aqueduct (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Olsen, H., The Making of a Stove, March 1916 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Olsen, Louis, Municipal Refuse Destructor Plant in Palo Alto, California, December 1914 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Piper, W. B., Crater Lake National Park and its Road Work, April 1915 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Richardson, W. H., Location Surveys in Alaska, March 1911 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sandstrom, A. C., Two Methods of Stream Gauging Used on the McKenzie Power Project, March 1913 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Scott, E. T., Hydraulic Dredging at Wilmington, California (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Seymour, D. J., Architectural Drafting, October 1914 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sharp, E. W., Dirt Coffer Dams (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Smith, Chauncey, Methods of Handling Concrete on Buildings, November 1912 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Stocklmeier, Louis, Modern Irrigation, September 1915 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Swanson, C. R., The Big Creek Power Plant, October 1913 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Thomas, W. H., Timber Estimating, March 1911 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Waterman, H. A., Power Line Construction (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Wells, J. B., The Construction of the Chamber Building of a Sulphuric Acid Plant (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Wong, Ralph Buck-Hond, Railway in China, November 1915 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - No author
    - Construction of Lateral Ditches on the Sacramento Valley Irrigation Project (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - East Contra Cost Irrigation System (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Railway Revaluation (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Sewerage Disposal in Southern California (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Some Results of Tests on Beams Designed After the Ransome (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - The South Bay Bulkhead (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - [Summer's Work in Salt Lake, Utah, Engineering Firm] (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Topographical Surveying with Aneroid Barometer (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - The Washington State Highway Department (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - The Water Conservation Association of the Santa Ana River (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - original index (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Abstracts and excerpts from annual report of committee on student chapters to board of direction, 1933-1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Abstract from stenographic record of conference of student chapter representatives, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Alumni directory correspondence, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Annual report of the Stanford chapter, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- A. S. C. E. manuals, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Circular of information regarding the Stanford University student chapter of the A. S. C. E., 1921 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Constitution and related correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Engineers' Council for Professional Development, fifth annual report, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Initiation, 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Papers read before the A. S. C. E. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - San Francisco Chapter of Amer. Soc. of Civil Engrs. Meeting of Dec. 21, 1920, Attended by K. H. Swanholm and L. D. Wilbur
  - Wilbur, Lyman D., The Los Angeles Aqueduct, January 1921
  - Fish, L. S., Some Engineering Problems Incident to the Production of Petroleum, November 1920
  - Lawler, Harry C., Construction of County Highway Bridge Spanning Salinas River at Palo Robles, California
- Photographs, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Picnic at C. C. Kennedy's, June 5, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Scholarship plan, 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Spring trip - Colorado River aqueduct, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
- Spring trip - Shasta Dam, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Trasurer's reports, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Mounted photographs of club members (1913 is a composite of individual shots into one photo), circa 1896 and 1906-1916 (Box 3)
- Mounted photographs of club members (1919 and 1920 images are somewhat damaged), 1917 -1925 (Box 4)
- Mounted photographs of club members, 1926 -1934 (Box 5)
- Secretary's book, 1905-1919 (Box 9)
  Includes constitution, membership lists, and minutes of meetings.